welcome
it's cohort one meeting 17 already and
it's September 23rd 2022 we're having
our first discussion of chapter seven in
the textbook
well
we have
many ways to go
we have questions on chapter seven that
people have been adding
we also have
um some
summaries and overviews and uh can walk
through the text directly
but first does anyone want to just raise
their hand or unmute and give
any thought that they had on chapter
seven their experience reading it
their understanding of where it's
situated in the textbook overall what
was in it or what was not in it
Etc
laughs
okay well
all uh open again please raise your
hands or write in the chat if you want
to address anything at any point
I want to open
um by acknowledging a lot of the
contributions ali uh made
and uh in some conversations that he and
I had earlier this week
that I believe
all of you cohort wonders will find
interesting
um but first let's just start with this
quotation we're going to start with the
opening quotation the chapter then I'm
going to surface some discussions with
Ali and then we're going to go into some
details of the chapter
so the quote is what I cannot create I
do not understand
by RF so
what does anyone think about that
quotation or what is it uh mean in this
context
um
I think
uh I mean it it's more applicable
applicable
applicable the more complex the the
thing is that you're trying to build but
like how could your generative what
priors or for what way could your
generative model create
and accurate prediction
of the operation of something or the
underlying dynamics of something if you
do not
kind of step-by-step
generate the afford and take the actions
that generate those affordances
I don't see any causal path to doing so
with help
like you would have to step through it
necessarily if it's
computationally like complex
so
that's most things in the world but
yeah
awesome it's like this is like the low
road answer like how can the generative
model have anything
like understanding
without generating you can't just have
it on the Shelf
and then someone
um has added the mild answer
we can't have understanding
just through mental envisioning
that the algorithms need to be
implemented for a learner's Journey
and then this is also um an even deeper
or stronger point
which
first and others have been
working on for a long time which is like
it's sentient artifacts in the world
that will be
the realization of active inference
it's not just like some nice derivations
Brock and then anyone else
I was just gonna add uh something about
hidden states there I mean it's again
coming back to computational complexity
but there's there's
things now that we're starting to build
that we don't really 100 understand all
of the Dynamics of what is or just in
general like we invent things that we
don't completely understand first and
then based on the observational
based on the evidence that we observe
that it is consistently exhibiting some
behavior that that directs our attention
that directs
where our generative model
pursues like
you know more observations but um
we're definitely getting towards a point
where that's like kind of no longer
going to be possible in the way that we
usually use them try to use math to just
shortcut stuff
where the the operation of the Dynamics
of the things that we're going to build
are necessarily going to be
they will be the proof of their
existence will be their own proof
awesome
okay so just fun you know starting
quotation upload that one for sure
though
um there's some detailed things about
[Music]
um
the examples
and I also uh and some of these I've
been working on everyone is welcome for
every chapter to be contributing on
these Pages like kind of just trying to
overview what these examples are because
a chapter
it states it up front yet I missed it
the first several times reading it like
these Illustrated models of
every color in the rainbow
are the section titles
and those are the functionalities that
are getting layered in
sometimes building on the same model
like there's like teammates version one
then there's team A's version two
other times it's switching between
models or showing two different models
that illustrate the same cognitive
functionality
other times the simulation outputs are
shown other times they're not so there's
like a lot of heterogeneity
in the observations in this chapter
but it really wasn't until I saw that
these
first paragraph words were the section
titles
that it made more sense how the chapter
was being like laid out
um so that's just kind of one
uh notes
um
Ollie do you wanna
raise any thoughts or describe a little
bit about our
discussion on like
how we're going to move forward on the
equations
okay
if you unmute then go for it otherwise
I'll um
let me see okay yes no Mike thank you
all good so
um we were discussing how there are
several layers
um as with other scriptural Traditions
there's levels of readings
so there's a level of reading
that is even
um more granular or below where we've
been currently targeting like here's
equation two five
there's a reading
for accessibility and understanding that
would potentially be like f open square
bracket Q comma y closed bracket equals
negative sign expectation over Q open
parenthesis X Etc so it's like the
reading of the notation
then the notation can be substituted for
terms in the active fontology which is
like the level that's being described
here
but this is not to be seen here
um
this is the level where notation could
be aligned across papers because their
notational reading would be different
but then they might be referring to the
same exact composition of the actin
fontology
then once the ontology definition has
been squared
the terms could be condensed into
meaningful units like accuracy
complexity
risk expected risk
that gives
um a symbolic in the more
conversational sense rather than in the
like notational sense
and then that's where
memes and themes and rhetoric around
like what active inference formalisms
say
start to arise
and then there's the consequences of
changes in relationships within and
outside the formalism
because it's kind of like we're all
there's this larger structure for like a
pomdp
and changing one variable if you're only
looking at like one view or one kind of
sub formalism
but you know turn it up to 11.
yet that might influence other variables
that aren't part of that formalism
itself
and so this is like a very open
question that touches on everything from
like the implications
of changes
to relationships that aren't formally
specified
for example the base graph the edges
reflect a certain type of relationship
as we've explored
but
changes from one can propagate
throughout a whole system potentially in
non-linear ways
so it's always going to be this kind of
open area
how changes
including like counterfactuals about the
formalism what if risks were situated
this way instead of that way or how does
that relate in this case like so this is
kind of an open one again people please
update it and and modify it
um but like some of these equations
which we'll get to so we'll come to why
we had that conversation in a 7.8 later
but that was like one um really
interesting
conversation
and then
[Music]
um
there was one other
okay
then just to kind of jump into a chapter
seven topic but also
kind of
reframe our Learning Journey
as we're all working through this for
the first time
um in the textbook group so
they wrote
um
this choice in the team Ace and then
Eric or anyone else I know that you had
some questions on the teammates
um or we can go to the earlier examples
but
this choice of what to do do you seek
out the informative cue and then go to
the arm that you've now reduced your
uncertainty about where the reward is so
do you take an epistemic action and then
have like a better chance of making the
pragmatically good choice
or do you just you know go and make the
pragmatic Choice do you take one step up
or do you take one step back for two
steps up
it speaks to the exploration
exploitation dilemma in Psychology and
machine learning a dilemma that's
resolved under active inference
so we were just cracking up because
um
first
a low familiarity learner might not know
what these terms are or like why it's
relevant to even talk about this
situation
familiarity might look like knowing
metaphors examples intuition some
relevant citations or historical
anecdotes about this
the understanding in terms of what the
active inference formalism says about
this you know if it's resolved under
active inference then understanding that
resolution
is about the basis
and then from understanding there could
be like further developments and
applications
um and then we'll we'll come to this but
what was making us
um
laugh was
surely there are parameterizations in
which the rat and the teammates
always does one thing or always does the
other
so it's not that the explore exploit
trade-off is simply resolved under
active inference even though people
commonly point to things like the
ability to rapidly switch between
exploratory and exploitative behavioral
policies
because there's parameterization of that
model and structure learning including
that
that has to be accomplished
such that the model can be in a kind of
critical point where it behaves
adaptively and thus in a situation
manages the explore exploit
tension under certain constraints
but how could it be said that active
inference resolves that dilemma
so maybe to um whomever wrote this one
what is happening yes please Eric click
classical Eric writing here so what what
about this
uh yeah I'm I'm kind of the Heckler at
the garden party here you can see in
most of my my comments and questions
um
but yeah I mean
maybe it's just best to I mean it's
maybe a bit of red than spoken but yeah
I don't I don't I don't see this as a
valid claim that
they well first of all it's not a I
don't know why they call it a dilemma
for psychology it's a trade-off
it's been understood for years and
there's ways of formalizing it and you
solve it through optimization
um
it might be a dilemma for a creature
because they don't they don't know you
know what they should do but then but
that's not a dilemma for the field
and then uh I guess the other
other paragraph is I I don't see that
they offer any resolution
all they do is they put it into the same
they use a Common Language free energy
they put exploration in and exploitation
into the same equation and call it you
know with this information based term
called free energy which is perfectly
valid that's great but that doesn't
resolve the problem because as you
pointed out
you've got parameters
and uh the designer or somebody has to
figure out what those relative weights
are the parameters are
and uh so you really have an advanced
any you know fundamentally simply by
using this free energy way of expressing
what the trade-off is as opposed to some
arbitrary measure called energy or
preference or something like that
so I just think that they're that it's
it's it doesn't help them when they over
claim which is my opinion man you could
convince me otherwise I'm open
um but it seems to me it doesn't help
them by by overstating their
contribution to
um
resolving exploration versus
exploitation
yes very insightful I actually totally
agree I purposely tried to not
mention it as a dilemma either I think
tensions trade-offs
um these are all valid
um but but that's that's uh like kind of
micro linguistic and a more serious
issue is that
claims
that do crystallize out from the text
and things that people can copy and
paste and quote you know if this were a
um a courtroom scenario I mean did you
say that active inference resolves
exploration exploitation
it's gonna have the answer has to be yes
it was claimed in the book
could somebody contextualize that like
it's providing a first principle's way
where there are tunable or learnable or
parameter sweepable
um features of models that sit at a
really well positioned
uh intersection of human
interpretability and manifolds of
relevant model variation
yes in an extremely charitable reading
one could kind of bring this up from
back from coming off over the edge back
onto the table
that would also
um make active inference less surprising
and less
realistically hyperbolic
and be part of this process of
[Music]
um
seeing the evidence in the realization
not in the um kind of ironic
like we have a different partitioning
of a statistical variable value so
nice points um Brock
um I guess I wanted to agree
with that and then also maybe play a
little Devil's Advocate because it's
like uh yeah
we're all it's all information
so
it's solved
um that's not really
just because it's
been formulated or renamed to something
pragmatic value epistemic value it
doesn't
seem like that resolves it or something
um
I'm wondering if the reading of that
though could be that not that there is a
TR there is still a trade-off
but that the Dilemma is that
what they're talking about is that the
trade-off like when do you explore or
when do you exploit not that there is a
trade-off but that that is
uh this last sentence and a half here of
um or the resolution stems from the
minimization of free energy
is that whether you would seek pragmatic
value or epistemic value
is conditioned on
which you your model believes to be
the free energy minimizing
choice
um
though it doesn't you still have the
Dilemma so to speak
um the trade-off
but which side of the trade-off you take
is maybe result
[Music]
um
by generative model here or not I don't
know
is that a day sprock I think the field
is set for a situational resolution
that may be as good or maybe better than
other ways that it's been addressed
but
it it comes down to the exact numbers
that are chosen so like in the example
of the teammates
um so we can look at for example this
0 6 and negative 6.
huh
what if it was negative 3 000 and
positive three thousand
and so this came up in the um live
stream 45 with Ryan Smith on the folk
psychology where the intensity of the
preference was represented
and so if the preference is so if you're
okay we prefer having more food
is that going to be a thousand versus
zero because if so even the scantist
probability
of achieving food will be pursued in
other words that model is going to be
parameterized way way way on one side
and it's going to exploit only or it's
only going to take locally um greedy
Behavior
whereas if someone said well my behavior
for food is point zero zero zero zero
one
then then maybe even the most obvious
strategy would not be undertaken because
it's so close to having a flat
preference
Y is 0.01 versus 3000 why is three
thousand too high and 0.01 too low
well it has to do with like the ratios
and the interactions of a lot of the
parameters
so it's it's not even going to be like
well my preference is three comma one
that is going to be just like two
parameters being drawn out from a
potentially massive parameterization of
a model
and so
preferences of just only speaking of
preferences maybe
um very hard to compare across
situations because it's not like plus
six
for the preference for food and negative
is it doesn't have a semantic meaning in
the world it's literally a model
parameterization
and so
then the question becomes
how
and this framework or this way of
um having of combining probabilistic
inference and energy-based inference
for strategic decision making how can
those parameters be tuned into a region
of Subspace or manifold where the
behavior is flexible and adaptive
so I think the stage is prepared for a
first principle's resolution
in very charitable reading sorry yes
please yeah I was just going to say Ali
shared this paper meta control uh of the
exploitation
uh exploration exploitation it's in the
nearby okay chat link
um nice
but that yeah that's that is it's it's
not that it solves it like in some
Grand it eliminates exploration
exploitation or that it even completely
currently yeah it's it's just the
affordance I guess seems to be there to
explain which one why like you're going
through that you know there's a
preference heavy here or heavy there and
it's you know not that it's
it's optimal right it's not not that it
makes sense or it's a depth adaptable or
anything like that necessarily just that
there is some causal through line Maybe
yes Eric
yeah um so I want to first read Ali's
comment here
um the critical point to establish is to
Define
um action selection as a balance between
maximization of expected reward and
expected Information Gain which are
functionals of posterior beliefs about
uh late states of the world
um so that touches on a different one of
the questions which I also wrote
comments on which is about the team A's
example in particular and we'll we may I
don't know if we'll have time but we may
get to that one today
um
so but the questions specifically I I
want to raise about this comment or
maybe this I guess is a quote
about
there being a balance between
maximization of expected reward versus
expected Information Gain
that's one way of having a trade-off but
you might look for a a
um an agent that only wants to maximize
reward
in the long run but in order to do that
that entails Information Gain and that
therefore gives a motivation for why you
want to
um attend to the other term the the the
information based you know information
or learning based term or knowledge uh
refining of State base based term but
that's in the service of the larger gain
and that's essentially what a um uh
reinforcement learning is tries to do is
say look we're going to look ahead so
that uh the moves we take now will bring
us advantage in the future and it's you
know there's a time discounting and all
that so that doesn't that that takes
away the idea of information it's as
being a value in and of itself but it's
only for a purpose and so I you know
well there's a specific you know
libraries that specifically with regard
to the team teammates example and a
different question
yeah
um thank you
the balance between
pragmatic and epistemic
is the optimization so that is the
question
and that is the critical point
and that's the situational balance that
bottling is going to be evolving around
it's like some situationally
um optimal or preferable
strategy around that
is the point
but pointing to the point is not the
resolution
does active inference provide us a
natural language grounded
first principles approach
it may
but
that is also not
um
dilemma resolution
so on to some questions but these are
really great points um
okay
this is uh just an example that quite of
a type of question that I encourage
people especially if they're going back
to the earlier chapters or just whenever
they feel like making a contribution of
this kind these are like super helpful
questions again the questions we write
some of them may be included in really
important educational materials not the
least of which many further textbook
groups but potentially even far beyond
that
so what would you ask somebody to
understand
their comprehension of the materials
so I just said what are the rows columns
and numbers in these equations
and it even says it in the text it's the
probability of the next state
so the next state is in the rows
and then the current state is in the
columns
and this gets distributed across
everything so that the rows and columns
sum to one
as any other transition probability
Matrix would be expected
to have
um so we don't need to discuss it um
unless somebody wants to go into a
little more detail but this is going to
be at the core of that third step of the
recipe which is you might have the
structural form from the second step of
the recipe in chapter six
and then the next step is to kind of
specify
or instantiate like
in code
what the dimensions are
of
these matrices this is just saying like
they are matrices there's some prior
tensor Matrix
some hidden State some transition Matrix
some emission Matrix
and this is like the structure step two
of the recipe
step three
how many rows and columns
and as Jacob and others have been
exploring
there's the rows and Columns of the
analytical representation with the
equations
and then there's how Pi mdp does it
and there's how different computational
realizations do it
um Jacob would you want to add anything
about like the dimensionality of these
matrices it could be interesting
yeah I mean uh
I can probably speak more to how Prime
DB deals with the dimensionality which
currently is probably
um unnecessarily as unnecessary like
redundancy to them uh like if you're
dealing with more complex State space or
rather more High dimensional State space
and you have different modalities that
you want to encode in these matrices you
uh the because you're then uh
performing Matrix multiplications you
need to keep the dimensions of
the matrices in those given modalities
equal at least in time DB not in not in
other
methods as far as I'm aware
um but that means that then you have
Dimensions Within These matrices that
don't contain any information so say you
have a a grid that you represent
for the likelihood mapping of
observation and uh
state state in physical world but then
you have another
um another type of observation like
where is another agent located with
respect to you like
um are they in a certain direction and
that might be represented by uh five
observations say like uh they're above
they're below they're to the right to
the left or not at all then you would
have then you would need to encode the
observation in the 9x9 Matrix but then
you need to replicate it five times
because it's that is the same for each
of those relative observations but then
when you want to encode the likelihood
mapping just for the second type of
observation uh I'm actually not entirely
sure
what that would be what I'm presuming
it's going to be like five by five but
then replicated nine times or something
like that
um
just so the dimensionality matches
because then you're doing inference over
both
modalities
and at least in Prime DP you're then
performing
um
Matrix multiplications over both of them
thank you Jakob one way I'm kind of like
seeing that is there's the sparsity of
the graph
but then in time DP or in in any given
computational implementation
the data structures including
potentially like auxiliary
data constructs
may have a dimensionality
that reflects
potentially at worst
a combination of the dimensionality of
other aspects
as part of even just a temp file that
you didn't even exactly specify there
might be some intermediates
stated or unstated intermediates whose
dimensionality
isn't
merely the dimensionality of the
analytical representation
it's a little bit of a subtle
implementational point
but this is
the mountain to climb to implement these
kinds of models
and also just while we're on this topic
I think it's one area where CAD CAD is
going to be very interesting to explore
in octoblock fronts package because we
also can imagine that the execution
order of certain operations even in a
single agent setting not just the
multi-agent setting is really relevant
so there's that question
all right so
figure 7.2 all right so the first
example is about a musician playing
music
um
we are not aware of this example being
used anywhere else
like the citations following those this
musical note type representation is not
like shown
um and previously we kind of discussed
how some of these Trace black and white
images are really
um ambiguous
because of being like intersecting black
lines and then of course
the um
the empty Square
so yes can you say where those lifelines
come from you want to dive into that
right now
yeah
um well
okay
the upper left each block line even
though it can be hard to trace them I
think they're just being shown like
representationally
their
beliefs about each note in the sequence
at each time step so the time steps are
on the x-axis
and the um
the uh
belief in terms of a probability are on
the y-axis
so initially right so there's some
there's some sort of and this gets to
another question that was raised but
maybe this is time to talk about it
there's some sort of engine some sort of
differential equation same you know
simulator or something running
underneath here right that
is not discussed in the chapter but
that's generating these belief curves
yes yes it's related to some functions
in Matlab and I was just going to
mention that because my sense from the
discrete model would be you'd have
five let's say points
on time zero
then you'd have five points on time one
so I thought well what is happening with
this kind of like you know little
fractal crash right here I mean what how
could you have a continuously
differentiable
um oscillating type Behavior
when all you're calculating analytically
is just one two three four five
then I thought is it meaning is is the
are the points actually at the midpoint
and there's a differential equation
that's sort of like ribboning
an action perception Loop through a
discrete time Matrix
but then
if this is a function that's evaluatable
at every point
aren't we in a continuous time setting
so wouldn't that have to imply
like a machinery for unpacking a
continuous time action perception cycle
from discrete time specification
so I agree
very much yeah
good yeah my guess is what they do is
they they've got their um you know these
equations if the free energy equations
and the the parameters are these
distributions okay what's your belief in
these different properties and
um those parameters evolve over time
through a differential equation because
you turn this you turn these things into
a differential equation and when you
change when you change the state
something like okay now we've got
another note comes in then that's what's
going to trigger
um the differential equation to go in a
different direction essentially and
that's what that's why you've got the
five discrete
kind of
um
regimes here or you know um Target
Target points that it kind of evolves to
um and then you know the next note comes
in and it now the boundary conditions
change essentially so your differential
equation takes you in a different
direction so I and I I recall that
there's something like um
you know you guys probably discussed
this more more than I paid attention but
there's some sort of universal solver
that they're providing
um so you just plug in your um State
your your Matrix matrices your
um
State equations or
your transition matrices and then it'll
solve it all for you and that may be
what this differential equation solver
is is about you think that that sounds
right
yes I think the um
yes when whenever variously in the
method sections and supplemental
sections of paper they'll say here in
the paper we're only specifying the
generative model and the matrices and
then we use standard routines to address
it now I don't think that has the um
it's not the Pinnacle of accessibility
and reproducibility
however it does at least use standard
routines but again those are not always
specified in the paper which is um an
issue
so it'll be important to regenerate
examples within SPM
and then also to use some of these
things that we were discussing with like
the ability to move between different
languages
um but like vbx variational Bayes X I
don't know what the x is actually for
um it is very it's one of the core
functions it is actually doing the
variational inference in SPM
and again SPM is like this sort of like
Chimera package because it arose
from the immediacies of needing to do
neuroimaging registration and dynamical
Analysis
that then broached into Dynamic causal
modeling
um random field Theory based statistical
testing permutation testing all these
areas that are not
um themselves formally linked per se but
rather useful as part of the toolkit of
a neuroimaging researcher
then
just as we were a little bit discussing
in
um like chapter two and of course many
times earlier
in that generalized Bayesian inferential
framework hierarchical modeling
including action
is actually not
the hardest thing
yes
implementing action is one thing but
treating action selection as inference
planning as inference it has some uh
challenges that arise
relative to Just Doing Time series
anticipation
um but then those functions became
compiled into SPM in a limited capacity
um so
they again they go through some of this
but but I think it's it's a key issue
um Ali we'll definitely look forward to
what the um free energy gradients are
um
but like what
where the continuous nature of these
curves and like why there are the
numbers that there are
one two three four five six seven eight
nine ten
now there's five notes
ten is two times five
like it's just there's a little bit more
that needs to be fleshed out there
um
and then one question that was like
again somewhere between testing or
comprehension and being clear about what
we're doing here
um and in this ambiguity we can ask it
without any bias
um the negative free energy gradients
I.E prediction errors
uh what
is a prediction error a free energy
calculation
well ignore a gradient for a second
free energy calculations are not
prediction errors prediction errors are
observations minus expectations so this
is like some finite value in the state
space of what is being measured
free energy is not that it references
potentially those variables but it does
things that we know about like KL
divergences and such okay so free energy
is not prediction error and that's a
huge difference between for example a um
predictive processing framework
and a free energy hierarchical
predictive architecture
Eric
but they're saying the gradient and free
energy is a prediction error
exactly so even if it were that's then
that was that was the next question
which was what's the difference between
free energy and the free energy
gradients are we talking about a
landscape
of derivatives of free Energies
or are we talking about what here like
is it being described as a gradient as a
landscape
and hence gradient-ish because it can be
calculated over
some
discrete bi-continuous State space
it's like five skyscrapers that you
could have derivatives over
in the y direction but you couldn't take
the partial X
or is it truly
um or is it a continuous landscape
that's just being tethered
to the discrete values in X but then
again that's the whole continuous
discrete question
or are the values
gradients
which has an even more complex
interpretation
so
we don't have the answers on these but
the these um
it's hard to understand how these
figures could have epistemic or
pragmatic value for Learners or
practitioners without some of these
questions being resolved
um
all right
um the first example this is just kind
of from this from walking through so the
first example was just hidden Markov
model
hidden States updating Through Time
Bayesian filter common filter this is
like just standard signal processing and
a Bayesian framework
um and we're going to see a lot of
Echoes of the step-by-step model stream
one they give an even simpler example
with static perception One Step
perception
and then
um go second to the dynamic case
then introduce action Pi policy and then
Nuance policy through like uncertainty
and so on
um so that's the first inferential case
they're then going to head into decision
making and planning as inference
so
um
we see policy being introduced as a
variable that
um
influences how States change Through
Time
does policy do that or does Action do
that
in the one step limit
policies our actions are affordances
but Pi is specifically reserved for
sequences of actions so is it that
sequences of actions like do that or is
it um you know is this the actual base
topology
um but nonetheless that architecture
allows the evaluation
of alternate policies in terms of their
relative expect uh variational or
expected free energy depending on
whether a one-step policy is
accomplishable with variational free
energy that's like the instantaneous
move
most consistent instantaneous maneuver
versus even one step in advance
is going to Broach into this whole
expected free energy space
um we had on 130
um so uh there's a really uh important
discussion
um Ozaki is also very interesting
researcher neural rhythms and so on
um
factorization is a really important
topic
and being able to distinguish like
neurologically what do we mean when we
talk about the what and the where stream
the dorsal and the ventral stream and
critiques of it Etc but just what and
where in the brain
and um then in the factor graphs and
computationally
because the unfactorized models
if we're just doing the all by all by
all by all those become intractable very
fast
and the specification of the sparsity of
the model
is one of the same in the variational
base framework as the factorization
of the model
so factorization is like kind of
focusing your search efforts on
manifolds
where you've constrained certain things
to be like linked or unlinked
that is what motivates the structure
learning problem
and the um need to have
um to not be locked into factorization
schemes
at a given level of analysis
um
okay
another just uh
question to to explore
um like here
we have the top of a half a figure four
three there's just one a matrix
so why are there two a matrices here
well it's not not an impossible question
and the symbols go a long way
here's the four locations that the
animal can be in starting position
bottom position left arm or right arm
then
here are the the it's five on The X here
because that bottom
can could reveal an r or reveal an l
in this case it reveals an R
and the food is honestly there
and then this is a second a matrix
that is um describing how location
is associated with
the food
non-abversive or positive
but this ties into the earlier
discussion like
it might be all one thing to say well
it's um four by five and then four by
three
but is this actually a four by five by
it can't be I I know it's not
Eric what do you think
yeah um and they mentioned and then
there's a tensor also
um which and the tensor means that
you're stacking this one
uh this image against the version where
the um reward is on the the left side so
the tensor is going to be four by uh
eight by two
so that makes sense for being the tensor
so this the state is another layer on
top of this the hidden State there's
another layer on top of that
yes
[Music]
um
section seven three so this would be a
fun
you know
um kind of like PhD qualifying level
question
just describe the whole team Ace
every row every column
and every value
why is it that way
so we're not going to type it out here
but
that is to understand that that example
and what what the B matrices are and
just what what and and to have
agility and just identifying the
differences between these matrices
numerically like pattern recognition
like oh here there's two ones here two
zeros here two zero zero two ones here
one and zero these stay the same
and then to be able to transpose that in
your understanding
to what this means in terms of
transition frequencies
every
place where there's a difference
it's a difference that makes a
difference
so being able to understand what those
are
is about understanding this example
and one can imagine especially if
they're wanting to make a application of
active inference that's more complex
than this 4x4
being fluent
with
how these matrices are constructed their
dimensionality how differences in the
generative process are Incorporated how
differences in the generative model are
Incorporated all these different
features are important
um this is yes Eric this is definitely
very important
um question agreed like
it it looks
extremely neural
this has and they these traces come up
all the time
um similarly here
we have three discrete time points
starting
going to the queue getting the L
and then going to the left arm
but then what is a step one and a half
is the one
all of these points
and then by two
their uncertainty is resolved the belief
about certain things goes to zero the
belief about the things goes to one
and this is just a pure interpolation
but
that is quite a specific interpolation
including what appear to be some like
dopaminergic spikes or something that
are not reflected at either of the time
points
my guess is that you've got three
different blocks there so if you take
the one as being the width you know
one-third of the way across the two is
another third and the three is another
third then that switch there that you
see happens as soon as you transition
from the one to the two
yes
oh although still there's even the
graphical interpolation
question like and it's just it's so it's
it's so easy to be like reading
you know just is it just a quirk of the
dashed line
but is it are there two dashed lines and
one two dashed lines diverged in a
neural Trace
um so it but it's um it's it's kind of
clear these ones the discrete
formulations are clearer
are rats prone to useless Behavior what
do you think
what useless Behavior
I I wrote it out okay okay yeah this is
good maybe we'll have time for today but
that's my most provocative
comment on this one and maybe we can
save that for next week
okay perfect let's pick up with this one
um and any other
questions then we'll um glance over the
visual cicade look at the learning
example
consider the hierarchical example
there's the maze then there's the
hierarchical example another
nested discrete meets neural continuous
Trace
and then we end on 7 squared so
thank you all
have an excellent day